hey aush students are you preparing for
your a push exam well here's the whole
course in just 30
[Music]
minutes period 1 begins in 1491 with the
study of Native American cultures before
European contact now natives developed
unique cultures based on climate and
geography in Central and South America
the Aztecs and the Mayas relied on maze
cultivation these tribes were large and
complex with intricate trade networks
sophisticated calendars and irrigation
systems in North America tribes were
mostly small and semi-nomadic indigenous
peoples on the Great Plains hunted
Buffalo and lived in teps while those
near the Great Lakes lived in more
permanent dwellings like long houses and
developed agriculture but everything
changed in 1492 when Christopher
Columbus arrived in the Americas this
leads us to one of the most important
concepts for period 1 which is the
Columbian Exchange this refers to the
exchange of plants animals ideas peoples
and diseases between the old world and
the new world European nations gained
well from exploiting these new resources
and experienced a population boom
because of new food sources and while
natives gained which aided in hunting
their populations were devastated by new
diseases like small poox Spanish
colonization also led to the rise of
conquistadors who were seeking gold God
and Glory College for's favorite example
is Hern and Cortez who brutally
conquered the Aztecs conquistadors also
set up the en comanda system to enslave
native populations and force them to
convert to Catholicism this also led to
the establishment of the Costa system
which was a racial hierarchy with
Spaniards at the top misos and mados in
the middle and Natives and enslaved
Africans at the bottom but many
questioned the harsh treatments of
natives which led to the valid delid
debates at these debates Catholic priest
balom de Lascassas supported converting
the natives but opposed the brutality of
the encomenda system but Juan hes de
seoa argued that the natives were
barbaric and that the Spanish had the
right to enslave them ultimately these
debates led to the decline of the
encomenda system but it was replaced
with the entos system which enslaved
Africans now Period 2 focuses on
colonization from 16007 to 1754 the
French established small settlements
like Quebec and New Orleans along the
great lakes and the Mississippi River
they maintained friendly relations with
natives which helped them profit from
fur trading and the French also focused
on Catholic conversion but through
peaceful Jesuit missionaries and the
Dutch were similar to the French
establishing the New Amsterdam Colony
for trade but English colonization was
characterized by mass migration
beginning with Jamestown in 1607 now
Jamestown was founded by a joint stock
company to make profit for its investors
and for the British crown tobacco
plantations became the basis of the
economy and the social structure of the
Chesapeake colonies which included
Virginia and Maryland but while settlers
in Virginia were mostly profit motivated
Maryland was founded as a refuge for
Catholics like the Chesapeake region the
southern colonies of North Carolina
South Carolina and Georgia also grew
cash crops but focused more on Rice
Indigo and sugar in South Carolina had
the heaviest concentration of African
enslaved laborers of all of the colonies
which led to Violent uprisings like the
stoner rebellion and the passage of
strict slave codes now the New England
colonies like Massachusetts were
established for religious reasons this
was demonstrated by Puritan leader John
winr City upon a hill Hill sermon these
strict religious societies were made up
of close-knit towns centered around the
church and the New England colonies had
rocky soil that was not suitable for
Plantation agriculture because of this
their economies depended on fishing
lumbering and trade through port cities
like Boston but they banished to centers
like an Hutchinson and Roger Williams
who went on to found Rhode Island and
the middle colonies were the most
ethnically and economically diverse In
1664 England took over Dutch New
Amsterdam and renamed it New York and
William Penn founded the Pennsylvania
colony on Quaker deals like freedom and
equality they had friendlier
relationships with Native Americans and
generally opposed slavery these colonies
were also called the Bread Basket
because they capitalized off of grain
farming they also profited from shipping
and lumbering because of Rapid
population growth tensions mounted
between colonists and Indigenous tribes
over land and resources this led to
Violent conflicts like The Poon Uprising
or King Philips War which often had
devastating consequences for natives
over time the 13 colonies developed a
distinct culture this was partially
because of the geographic distance and
the unique landscape but also because of
a unique tradition of self-government
this was seen through the Mayflower
Compact the Virginia House of Burgesses
and the Fundamental Orders of
Connecticut the colony's economies were
based on the theory of mercantilism
where a country grows Wealthy by
exporting more than it has to import in
an attempt to control colonial trade the
crown passed a series of Navigation Acts
but they were Loosely enforced under a
policy known as salutary neglect and in
the 1730s a religious revival known as
the first Great Awakening occurred led
by Jonathan Edwards and George
Whitefield Edwards brought people into
the church using fear with sermons like
sinners in the hands of an Angry God
while Whitefield inspired emotional
conversions at massive camp meetings so
the colonist began to question Church
Authority which also LED them to
question the authority of the British
crown and an example of colonists
questioning British Authority was
Bacon's Rebellion Nathaniel Bacon l a
violent Revolt of poor farmers in 1676
against Virginia's Royal Governor
William Berkeley over unfair treatment
and a lack of protection from attacks by
Native Americans This showed the growing
tensions between settlers and colonial
leaders this Rebellion also contributed
to the transition from indentured
servitude to the use of enslaved African
labor in the Virginia colony now period
3 starts in 1754 with the French and
Indian War this was part of a larger
conflict but unfolded in America because
of British expansion into the Ohio River
Valley which was controlled by French
Traders and Indigenous tribes the war
ended with the Treaty of Paris in 1763
drastically altering the relationship
between the colonist in the British
crown and in the same year pontiac's
Rebellion took place which led to the
passage of the Proclamation of 17 63
this banned settlement passed the
appalachin mountains to prevent further
native conflicts after the war Britain
was also left with a large amount of
debt this caused them to end the policy
of salutary neglect which angered the
colonists tensions mounted in the
colonies over new taxes like the Stamp
Act in 1765 groups like the Sons of
Liberty and the Daughters of Liberty
protested and famously cried no taxation
without representation and while the
1770 Boston Massacre angered the
colonist the 1773 Boston Tea Party
angered the crown leading to the passage
of the Intolerable Acts despite attempts
to maintain peace at the First
Continental Congress shots were fired at
Lexington and Concord leading to the
Second Continental Congress and after
Thomas Payne's Common Sense convinced
colonists that Independence was the best
route the Declaration of Independence
was drafted on July 4th 1776 both
documents were inspired by Enlightenment
ideals like republicanism and natural
rights despite being The Underdogs the
Continental Army won the American
Revolution because of George
Washington's leadership the use of
Guerilla Warfare tactics and support of
allies like the French and the war ended
in 1783 with another Treaty of Paris and
granted America its independence but the
new nation had all sorts of problems
mostly because leaders created an
intentionally weak government called The
Articles of Confederation the Articles
lacked the power to tax or create a
national currency and there was only a
legislative branch which allowed one
vote per state with nine votes needed to
pass a law and 13 to amend the Articles
the federal government had little power
this was demonstrated when they failed
to put down Shay's Rebellion now this
led to the Constitutional Convention in
1787 where delegates proposed a series
of compromises for the new government
the Great Compromise established a by
Camal legislature and the controversial
3- fifths compromise appeased
Southerners by partially counting
enslave people towards representation
the Constitution also included ideas
like separation of powers checks and
balances and federalism but Federalists
and Anti-Federalists debated
ratification of the new constitution
Anti-Federalists feared the new
government was too strong and pushed for
a Bill of Rights but Federalists who
were led by Alexander Hamilton published
The Federalist Papers to argue for the
new stronger government ultimately the
the Constitution was ratified in 1789
and the Bill of Rights was added to
protect civil liberties under the new
constitution George Washington was
unanimously elected as America's first
president he set many precedents while
in office like the establishment of the
first presidential cabinet and the show
of federal power during the Whiskey
Rebellion he also set the two-term
tradition by stepping down from office
in 1796 this is where he issued the
famous farewell address which is one of
the most important documents in American
history in it he warned Americans to
stay out of the Affairs of Europe and to
avoid political parties but we also see
Americans first political parties in
Period 3 the Federalist Party led by
Alexander Hamilton wanted an Economy
based on trade and Manufacturing
supported the national bank and favored
a loose interpretation of the
Constitution but Thomas Jefferson's
Democratic Republican party wanted an
agrarian Nation opposed the national
bank and supported a strict
interpretation of the Constitution now
the American Revolution also inspired
revolutions across the globe like in
France and in Haiti and the French
Revolution was a major foreign policy
argument for these political parties
period 3 ends with the presidency of
John Adams who was America's only
Federalist president his term was
overshadowed by the Quasi war with
France and he lost reelection in part
due to the Alien and Sedition Acts
period 4 starts in 1800 with the
election of America's first Democratic
Republican Thomas Jefferson he believed
in a strict interpretation of the
Constitution limited Federal power and
an Economy based on farming and in 1803
Jefferson approved the Louisiana
Purchase which doubled the size of the
United States foreign policy dominated
much of Jefferson's presidency as he was
forced to respond to the barbery Pirates
and the Chesapeake leopard Affair and
like Washington and Adams before him he
was plagued by ongoing conflicts between
England and France which led to the
passage of the 1807 Embargo Act and
while it was meant to protect American
industry and maintain neutrality it hurt
the American economy next is James
Madison who served two terms and oversaw
the War of 1812 this was fought over the
British impressment of American Sailors
and the British military presence in
Western forts this war saw the burning
of the White House the creation of the
star spangle banner and the Battle of
New Orleans and the Hartford Convention
which was led by Federalists to oppose
the war led to the party's collapse the
war ended in 1814 with the Treaty of
gent elected in 1816 James Monroe served
during a period of prosperity and
National Unity that followed the War of
1812 and his presidency is often
referred to as the Era of Good Feelings
because there was only one political
party which was the Democratic
Republicans Monroe famously issued the
Monroe Doctrine which warned European
powers to stay out of the Western
Hemisphere he was also president when
Henry Clay's Missouri Compromise was
passed to maintain the balance of free
and slave states with the establishment
of the 3630 line but the Era of Good
Feelings ended with the corrupt bargain
election of John Quincy Adams in 1824
the early 1800 so an expansion of
democracy with universal white male
suffrage enabling Democrat Andrew
Jackson to become the first Common Man
president in 1828 Jacksonian Democracy
and Jeffersonian democracy were similar
because both supported an agrarian
nation and states rights but opposed the
National Bank but Jackson's presidency
was extremely controversial between his
Wars with the National Banks and his
Indian Removal which led to the Trail of
Tears another major controversy under
the Jackson administration was the the
Nullification Crisis where South
Carolina's John C Calhoun refused to
comply with the 1828 tariff which was
known as the Tariff of Abominations now
in response to Jackson's policies the
wig party was formed under the
leadership of Henry Clay the wig
supported a strong central government
and the growth of the American economy
through trade and Manufacturing this was
promoted by Henry Clay's American system
which supported a high protective tariff
a Second National Bank and internal
improvements now period 4 also focuses
on the market Revolution textile mills
like the low Mills grew because of the
invention of the power loom and the
spinning jenny these factories also
hired unskilled workers like women
immigrants and even children and while
Northern factories adopted Eli Whitney's
interchangeable parts Southern
plantations used his cotton genene to
significantly increase cotton production
meanwhile Western Farmers used the steel
plow and the mechanical reaper to tackle
the tough soil this coincided with the
transportation Revolution that connected
the nation new steam engines led to the
creation of railroads and Robert Fon
Steamboat and the Eerie Canal and the
Cumberland Road further connected
Regional economies the rapid change
following industrialization also
coincided with a Second Great Awakening
leaders like Charles grandis and Finny
held large camp meetings and churches s
surges and attendance new denominations
were also formed like the Mormon church
this wave of religious enthusiasm
inspired social and moral reform
movements known as the antibellum
reforms many emerged to speak out
against the ills of slavery with the
abolition movement like Frederick
Douglas and William white Garrison and
grips like the women's Christian
Temperance Union reform to speak out
against the use of alcohol women also
gathered to fight for women's equality
and suffrage like at The senica Falls
Convention where they drafted the
Declaration of Sentiments this movement
was spearheaded by women like Elizabeth
Katie Stanton and Luc shamad and social
movements sprung up for hospital prison
and education reform period 5 starts in
1844 with the election of James K pulk
he supported Manifest Destiny which
argued that it was America's god-given
duty to spread from coast to coast Paul
campaigned on an expansionist slogan 544
year fight and approved the annexation
of Texas this led to boundary disputes
near the Rio Grande river which
ultimately caus the Mexican-American War
the war ended in 1848 with the Treaty of
Guadalupe hialgo and America gained
present day Arizona New Mexico Utah
Nevada and California and shortly after
gold was discovered in California which
led to the California Gold Rush but all
of this new land led to debates over
whether or not to allow slavery in these
new territories Henry Clay attempted to
ease these tensions with the Compromise
of 1850 this included the addition of
California as a free state and popular
sovereignty for Utah and New Mexico and
while it banned the slave trade in
Washington DC had also strengthened the
Fugitive Slave Act which angered
abolitionists these continued debates
over slavery are a major focus of period
5 harri Tubman famously helped enslave
people escaped through the Underground
Railroad while Harry psto published
Uncle Tom's Cabin to bring awareness to
the horror of enslavement but the South
responded with arguments defending
slavery like George Fitz who's sociology
of the South intentions reached a
boiling point in 1854 with the Kansas
Nebraska Act which allowed for popular
sovereignty in both Kansas and the
Nebraska territory Pro and anti-slavery
groups flooded into these territories in
hopes of swaying votes violence erupted
and more than 50 people died and what
became known as Bleeding Kansas violence
was also seen on the floor of the US
Senate in a heated debate over slavery
when Southerner Preston Brooks attacked
Massachusetts senator Charles suner with
his Cane period 5 also saw the
controversial Dread Scott decision in
1857 chief justice Roger T ruled that
African-Americans were not US citizens
and that Scott had no constitutional
rights this also overturned the Missouri
Compromise in the same year John Brown
raided Harper's fery in an attempt to
start an armed slave Uprising
Southerners viewed him as an extremist
and feared the rise of violent and
radical abolition while some Northerners
viewed Brown as a martyr these debates
over slavery and disagreements over
protective tariffs and states rights
continued to increase tensions between
the North and the South all of this came
to a head with the election of
Republican Abraham Lincoln in 1860
southern states were convinced that
Lincoln would abolish slavery and began
seceding from the Union forming the
Confederate States of America and when
shots were fired at Fort Suter the Civil
War officially began while many
Northerners believed that the war would
be quick it dragged on for four long
years the South had Superior generals
and a commitment to the cause but the
north ultimately won the war because it
had money infrastructure a higher
population and President Lincoln's
leadership during the war Lincoln
instituted a draft suspended habus
Corpus in the border states and issued
the Emancipation Proclamation which
prevented the south from Gaining
European support after the war ended in
186 65 America entered a period known as
reconstruction to bring the former
Confederate states back into the union
and while President Andrew Johnson and
Radical Republicans in Congress
disagreed about the best course of
action radicals ultimately controlled
this process with military
reconstruction and the Freeman's Bureau
was one of the biggest successes of
reconstruction it provided Necessities
like food shelter and education to newly
freed African-Americans and Congress
also passed the Reconstruction
amendments the 13th abolished slavery
the 14th defined citizenship and
guaranteed equ protection and the 15th
granted all men the right to vote this
led to the election of African-Americans
to Congress for the first time like
herum Rebels but Reconstruction had many
failures although slavery had ended it
was replaced with the sharecropping
system which left African-Americans
working on plantations and in a cycle of
debt and Southern States disenfranchised
black voters by using pole taxes and
literacy tests and the rise of black
codes Jim Crow laws and white supremacy
groups like the KKK hindered progress
period 5 ends with the compromise of 18
77 Republican Rutherford B Hayes was
chosen as the president in return for
removing troops from the south ending
reconstruction period expands from 1865
to 1898 the Gilded Age saw the
development of Corporations like us
steel and standard oil these businesses
were run by wealthy industrial
capitalists like Andrew Carnegie and
John de Rockefeller new business
practices like the formation of trusts
and vertical and horizontal integration
enabled these companies to form
monopolies this was possible because of
a string of Republican presidents who
supported Le Fair policies workers
endured long hours low pay and poor
conditions this led to the rise of labor
unions like the American Federation of
Labor who use strikes and collective
bargaining to fight for change but
strikes like the great Railroad Strike
and the Pullman Strike were unsuccessful
because the government sided with
businesses unions were also blamed for
Chicago's Hay Market Square riot but
during this time there were some
attempts to control businesses like the
Sherman Antitrust Act and the Interstate
Commerce Commission new philosophies
also emerged during the guilded age for
example social Darwinism was the
economic form of Darwin's survival of
the fittest while Andrew Carnegie's
gospel of wealth argued that it was the
duty of the wealthy to donate their
wealth to fund libraries schools and
Community projects also the social
gospel movement aimed to apply Christian
principles to the problems caused by
industrialization and urbanization this
period also saw the rise of immigration
and urbanization tenan houses were built
for the poor and for immigrants who
often settled in ethnic neighborhoods
while the antum period saw immigration
mostly from Germany and Ireland these
new immigrants mostly came from Southern
and Eastern Europe and political
machines like Tam Hall often took
advantage of these immigrants by trading
services for votes nativism also
increased especially against Chinese
immigrants who arrived on the west coast
which led to the passage of the Chinese
Exclusion Act As Americans moved West
under the Homestead Act corporations
also looked West the Transcontinental
Railroad was finally completed in 1869
connecting the East and West coasts and
railroads expanded across the west
through government land grants Mining
and ranching were also set up in western
territories but the rapid development of
the West had devastating consequences
for Native Americans who inhabited these
lands and led to the decimation of
Buffalo populations intentions exploded
in the plains Wars which dominated the
late 1800s tribes like the nesp and the
lakotas Su fought to maintain their
ancestral lands and their autonomy but
the US Army devastated these tribes at
tragic events like the S Creek Massacre
and it wounded me despite the efforts of
indigenous peoples like the Ghost Dance
Movement or their victory at Little Big
Horn these tribes were ultimately
defeated and the Decades of government
injustices against Native Americans was
exposed in Helen Hunt Jackson's book A
Century of Dishonor meanwhile
assimilation is scho like the infamous
Carlile School sought to erase native
culture and force conversion to
Christianity and the 1887 Daw severalty
act broke up tribal lands offering
citizenship to natives who agreed to
assimilate industry also expanded in the
South Atlanta journalist Henry Grady
promoted what he called a new South a
South that was focused on economic
diversity Southern cities like
Birmingham and Memphis built steel mills
and lumber plants while Georgia and the
Carolinas built textile factories and
Virginia established tobacco
manufacturing plants and finally period
6 saw the rise of the popul movement
populists were mostly farmers who
struggled with low crop prices and debt
their Omaha platform supported the
unlimited coinage of silver a graduated
income tax and the direct election of
senators their platform was adopted by
Democrat candidate William Jennings
Bryan in the election of 1896 where he
gave the famous Cross of gold speech
supporting B metalism but he lost to
Republican candidate William McKinley
period 7 covers 1890 to 1945 in 1890
Frederick Jackson Turner wrote his
Frontier Thesis which argued that the
frontier was officially closed this
trans positioned America from Manifest
Destiny and into the age of Imperialism
and President McKinley was America's
first imperialist president he annexed
Hawaii and brought America into the
Spanish American war after the sinking
of the USS Main and the publication of
the delhom letter the war ended with the
Treaty of Paris and the US gained access
to Puerto Rico Guam Cuba and the
Philippines which led to the Philippine
American war but Americans debated
imperialism some believ that it was
necessary to compete with Europe While
others argued that it was White Man's
Burden to spread American culture but
anti-imperialists believed imperialis M
contradicted American values like
freedom and equality president Theodore
Roosevelt was also an imperialist his
Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe
Doctrine stated that the US had the
right to intervene in Latin America to
maintain peace and stability his foreign
policy was called big stick diplomacy
and an example was when Roosevelt
supported the Panamanian independence
movement to build the Panama Canal
period 7 also includes the Progressive
Movement which was a period of social
activism and political reform mck ring
journalists inspired reform by exposing
social problems and political corruption
Ida Tarbell exposed Standard Oil and Ida
Wells spoke out against lynching and
Upton clar's the jungle exposed the meat
packing industry while Jacob Reese
photographed poor living conditions in
cities Roosevelt was also the first
progressive president his Square Deal
promoted consumer protection controlling
corporations and conservation of
resources he did this by breaking up
trust creating national parks and
establishing the Food and Drug
Administration President William Howard
Taft and woodro Wilson also oversaw
Progressive reforms including the
passage of the 16th through the 19th
amendments and an economic reform was
achieved with the Clayton Anti-Trust Act
and the creation of the Federal Reserve
but reform took a backseat when World
War I broke out in Europe in 1914 while
President Wilson maintained neutrality
the nation transitioned to wartime
production to support the Allied cause
and after years of German unrestricted
submarine warfare and the publication of
the Zimmerman Telegram America joined
the war in 1917 during the war civil
liberties were restricted with the
Espionage and Sedition Acts and federal
power was expanded through new
organizations like the War Industries
Board President Wilson created a plan to
avoid future conflicts called the 14
points which he hoped would be added to
the Treaty of Versa but the Senate
refused to ratify the treaty mostly
because of the controversial League of
Nations reservationists like Henry kabat
Lodge opposed the League of Nations
because they feared it would interfere
with American autonomy World War I was
followed by a period of prosperity and
social change called The Roaring 20s
during this time Americans bought cars
and new appliances women who had
recently gained the right to vote also
expressed themselves with their new
flapper style in the mass Exodus of that
African-Americans from the Jim Crow
South to the north which is known as The
Great Migration led to the Harlem
Renaissance this was a flourishing of
Black Culture through ART poetry and
jazz music and Young Americans danced to
that music at clubs and speak easys
these were secret underground clubs that
served alcohol since the 18th amendment
created a period known as prohibition
but the rapid changes of the 1920s faced
backlash nativism increased after the
war leading to immigration quota laws
and the Red Scare and racial tension
sparked several race riots like the
Tulsa Race Massacre and relig ious
fundamentalism opposed the teaching of
evolution as seen in the Scopes Monkey
Trial but the Roaring 20s ended with the
stock market crash in October of 1929
which started the Great Depression the
economic crisis was caused by excessive
spending on credit buying stocks on
margin and a crisis in farming Americans
lost their savings jobs and homes under
the poor leadership of president Herbert
Hoover who failed to take action but in
the election of 1932 Franklin D
Roosevelt promised the American people
relief recovery and reform with his new
deal relief for the unemployed included
programs like the works progress
administration he also introduced
reforms like the Federal Deposit
Insurance Corporation and Social
Security but the New Deal was criticized
for being an overreach of federal power
especially by the Supreme Court
ultimately the Great Depression ended
with the outbreak of World War II FDR
attempted to stay neutral but approve
the cash and carry and Len Le programs
to provide Aid to the Allied Forces he
also instituted America's first
peacetime draft but the Japanese attack
on Pro Harbor on December 7th 1941
forced America to join the war this also
led to discrimination against Japanese
Americans and Japanese interment like
World War I women worked in factories
making ammunition and airplanes but
could also serve in the women's Army
Corps other groups like The Tuskegee
Airmen and the Navajo Co talkers were
instrumental in American victory as well
while the war in Europe ended with
German defeat not long after D-Day the
war in the Pacific continued using the
research and development from the
Manhattan Project President Harry Truman
chose to use the atomic bomb to force
the Japanese to surrender so period 7
concludes with the end of World War II
and the formation of the United Nations
ations both of which have significant
effects on American foreign policy
moving forward period 8 spans from 1945
to 1980 after World War II America
experienced a period of prosperity with
the passage of the GI Bill families grew
and moved into suburbs like levit toown
Conformity and consumerism were the norm
with husbands who commuted to work on
Eisenhower's interstate system while
wives bought the latest consumer
appliances and cared for the family but
Young Americans rebelled against
Conformity like the Beats this coincided
with the developing Cold War which was a
period of tension between the United
States and the Soviet Union at home
Americans feared communism during a
second Red Scare this hysteria was
driven by the house and Americans
Activities Committee and senator Joseph
McCarthy as well as the convictions of
aler his and the rosenbergs meanwhile
Cold War foreign policy centered on
containing communism which was first
proposed in George kennan's Long
Telegram this was seen through the
Marshall Plan the Truman Doctrine and
the Eisenhower Doctrine the Eisenhower
Administration also used brinkmanship to
deter Soviet aggression later policies
include Kennedy's less aggressive
flexible response while Nixon dayon
sought to ease tensions there are a few
critical Cold War events that you want
to know the first challenge was the
Berlin blockade and the Berlin airlift
in 1948 America responded to the Soviet
blockade of Berlin by airlifting
supplies to West berliners and the
Korean War which was fought between 1950
and 1953 is important because it was the
first proxy war of the Cold War it
showed that both sides were willing to
go to war over their ideals even if it
was indirect and the Cuban Missile
Crisis is the closest America and the
Soviet Union were to an allout nuclear
war after Americans discovered the
installation of Soviet missiles in Cuba
Kennedy and kushev were able to
negotiate a diplomatic solution which
help thaw tensions the Vietnam War also
occurred in periodate out of fear of a
domino effect in Asia Eisenhower and
Kennedy first sent military advisers but
both refused to send combat troops this
changed after the Gulf of tonan incident
when President Johnson sent 500,000
American troops within 4 years the war
was met with heavy opposition at home as
the counterculture movement Pro protest
to the draft and families saw the war
from their televisions events like the
melee Massacre and the publishing of the
Pentagon papers also increased Americans
distrust in the government the Civil
Rights Movement also gained momentum in
the 1950s and 1960s the movement saw
early victories like the brown be the
Board of Education case in the
Montgomery Bus Boycott which was started
by Rosa Parks groups like Martin Luther
King Jr's Southern Christian leadership
conference and the Student Nonviolent
Coordinating Committee fought for
equality through marches demonstrations
and sens and after being arrested in 19
63 King wrote the famous letters from A
Birmingham Jail where he stressed the
importance of Civil Disobedience and
these tactics were successful leading to
the passage of the Civil Rights Act in
1964 and the Voting Rights Act in 1965
but some opposed the slow pace of the
movement like Malcolm X and the Black
Panthers who supported more direct
confrontation and black nationalism
while Johnson oversaw new civil rights
legislation he also implemented new
programs to combat poverty Johnson's
Great Society established Medicare
Medicaid project Head Start and other
programs for lowincome families but like
the New Deal it met resistance over
increased government spending and
providing welfare the success of the
Civil Rights Movement inspired other
groups to fight for change Betty freedan
published The Feminine Mystique
inspiring women to challenge traditional
gender Norms she also helped establish
the National Organization for Women and
pushed for an equal rights amendment but
some conservatives like Phyllis Schley
opposed the bill and fought to maintain
traditional gender roles Latino
Americans fought for equality with the
Cho movement and Caesar Chavez with the
United workers Association while Native
Americans fought with organizations like
the American Indian movement and while
lgbtq plus groups advocated for safety
in equality they saw little changes as
demonstrated by The Stonewall riots
another movement to know is the
environmentalist movement which was
inspired by Rachel Carson's book Silent
Spring she exposed the use of damaging
pollutants and chemicals like DDT this
inspired the creation of the
Environmental Protection Agency and the
passage of the Clean Air Act and the
Clean Water Act it also led to the
celebration of America's first Earth Day
period 8 ends with Jimmy Carter's
Administration even though he
successfully negotiated the Camp David
Accords Carter was criticized for a weak
economy because of continued stagflation
and for his failure to negotiate the
release of American hostages in Iran
period 9 starts in 1980 with the
election of Ronald Reagan between the
Iranian hostage crisis and a wave of
conservativism Republican Ronald Reagan
won the presidency in the election of
1980 his campaign focused on shrinking
the size of the federal government
decreasing spending and supply side
economics which is known as Reaganomics
but while Reagan decreased spending by
cutting Great Society programs he
increased defense spending for example
he supported the Strategic Defense
Initiative which is also known as Star
Wars in the ongoing arms race with the
Soviet Union but Reaganomics was
criticized because corporations and the
wealthy benefited from his tax cuts
while many argued these benefits failed
to trickle down to the working class
Reagan was also criticized for his role
in the Iran Contra affair but most of
Reagan's foreign policy was focused on
ending the Cold War he and Gorbachev
focused on more diplomatic Solutions
including his famous speech at the
Berlin Wall ultimately the Cold War
ended in 1991 under President George HW
Bush with the fall of the Berlin wall
and the collapse of the Soviet Union for
the remainder of period 9 foreign policy
is focused on the growing crisis in the
Middle East for example President Bush
sent American forces into Kuwait during
the Gulf War which is also known as
Operation Desert Storm the goal was to
prevent further aggression from Saddam
Hussein the Iraqi leader who had invaded
Kuwait and in 2001 President George W
bush announced a war on terror following
the SE member 11th 2001 attacks on the
World Trade Center American forces were
dispatched in operation Iraqi freedom
and operation enduring freedom to combat
terrorism remove Saddam Hussein from
power and to capture Osama Bin Laden
meanwhile domestic policy in period 9 is
dominated by increasing political
polarization since 1980 the Democrat and
Republican parties have intensely
debated issues like federal spending and
immigration policies as well as social
issues like abortion and gay marriage
and the parties argued over how the
federal government should respond to
National crisis IES like the Great
Recession and the covid-19 pandemic
migration and immigration are also a big
part of period 9 the Midwest which was
once known as the steel belt transformed
into the Rust Belt because of a decline
in manufacturing and overseas
competition and international migration
from Latin America and from Asia
increased dramatically which led to
political debates and an increase in
nativism the new immigrants influenced
American culture and supplied the
economy with an important labor force
and the final topic of period 9 is
globalization with new technologies like
personal computers the Internet cell
phones and social media the world is
more interconnected than ever economies
are also connected through groups like
The World Trade Organization and the
North American free trade agreement so
to bring us full circle globalization is
like the Columbian Exchange that we
talked about in period 1 it brings
people goods and ideas closer together
and it aims to grow Global economies
through increased trade new Industries
and new markets so that's a quick walkr
of each period in a push and if you need
more help like study guides timelines
and summary videos make sure you check
out the ultimate review packet